<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-wdenniss-oauth-device-posture-00"
    ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title>OAuth 2.0 Device Posture Signals</title>

    <author fullname="William Denniss" initials="W." surname="Denniss">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 650-253-0000</phone>
        <facsimile/>
        <email>wdenniss@google.com</email>
        <uri>http://google.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Karl McGuinness" initials="KM" surname="McGuinness">
      <organization>Okta</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>301 Brannan St.</street>
          <city>San Francisco</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94107</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone/>
        <facsimile/>
        <email>kmcguinness@okta.com</email>
        <uri>https://www.okta.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="11" month="March" year="2017"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>OAuth Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        Enterprise and security focused OAuth providers typically want
        additional signals to confirm user presence when users return to
        previously authorized apps. Rather than requiring a full
        reauthentication, or require enrollment in a mobile device
        management solution, some authorization servers may be willing to accept
        device posture signals from the app, like the fact that device has a
        lock screen, as confirmation of user presence. This document details how
        OAuth native app clients can communicate device posture signals to OAuth
        providers.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
      <t>
        Users who follow strong security practices on their devices - such
        as configuring screen locks, and not enabling admin privileges (commonly
        known as "rooting" or "jailbreaking") - shouldn't need to reauthenticate
        frequently to the individual apps on their device.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification details how apps can send device posture signals to
        the OAuth Token Endpoint, enabling it to enforce device policy
        compliance, and avoid the need for reauthentication in some cases.
      </t>
      <t>
        It is designed to provide a mechanism
        for honest apps to communicate device posture. By itself it doesn't
        protect against malicious users, dishonest apps, or compromised devices,
        but the signal format described could carry signals that do.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Notational Conventions" anchor="NotationalConventions">
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
        and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
        Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels
        <xref target='RFC2119' />. If these words are used without being spelled
        in uppercase then they are to be interpreted with their normal natural
        language meanings.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology" anchor="terminology">
      <t>
        In addition to the terms defined in referenced specifications, this
        document uses the following terms:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="MDM"><vspace/>
            Mobile Device Management.
          </t>

          <t hangText="EMM"><vspace/>
            Enterprise Mobility Management.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Device Posture Signal Dictionary" anchor="device_posture_signals">
      <t>
        The device posture is a dictionary of signals asserted
        by the app about the device. The structure is send as an added
        parameter in several places during the OAuth flow, as documented in the
        subsequent sections.
      </t>
      <t>
        All device posture keys are OPTIONAL and MUST only be set when the
        attribute can be obtained by the app. The standard attribute keys are as
        follows:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="screen_lock"><vspace/>
          Boolean. True if the device has a screen lock, such as a pin, pattern
          biometric, etc.
          </t>

          <t hangText="root_privileges"><vspace/>
          Boolean. True if user apps can access root device privileges. For mobile
          operating systems, known as "jailbreaking" on iOS and "rooting" on
          Android.
          </t>

          <t hangText="full_disk_encryption"><vspace/>
          Boolean. True if data stored on the device is fully encrypted at rest.
          </t>

          <t hangText="device_id"><vspace/>
          String. A unique identifier for the device.
          </t>

          <t hangText="device_os"><vspace/>
          String. The name of the operating system running on the device such as
          "iOS" or "Android".
          </t>

          <t hangText="device_os_version"><vspace/>
          String. The current version of the operating system.
          </t>

          <t hangText="device_vendor"><vspace/>
          String. The vendor of the device such as "Apple" or "Google".
          </t>

          <t hangText="device_model"><vspace/>
          String. The model of the device such as "iPhone X" or "Pixel 2".
          </t>

          <t hangText="device_attestation"> <vspace/>
          Dictionary. An attestation from the operating system, containing
          a signed-statement about the device and/or the app. The format is
          a dictionary, the specifics of which depends on the operating system.
          </t>

          <t hangText="app_id"><vspace/>
          String. The platform-specific identifier (URI) for the application.
          For Android, the format of the URI is android:apk-key-hash:&lt;hash-of-apk-signing-cert&gt;.
          For iOS, the format of URI is ios:bundle-id:&lt;ios-bundle-id-of-app&gt;.
          </t>

          <t hangText="app_managed"><vspace/>
          Boolean. True if the app is managed by a MDM/EMM system.
          </t>

        </list>
      </t>

	<t>
    An example device posture dictionary:
  </t>
  <t>
	  <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "screen_lock": true,
    "root_privileges": false,
    "full_disk_encryption": true,
    "device_id": "6bdde1e8-0667-40f9-9993-16aa52ee6b38",
    "device_os": "iOS",
    "device_os_version": "11.1",
    "device_vendor": "Apple",
    "device_model": "iPhone X",
    "app_id": "ios:bundle-id:com.example.myapp",
    "app_managed": false
}]]></artwork></figure>
	</t>
    </section>



    <section title="Authorization Request Device Posture Hint" anchor="authorization_request">
      <t>
        Clients MAY send the device posture signal dictionary to the authorization server
        in the authorization request. These signals, except for those that are
        signed and bound to the device are susceptible to client-side
        modification by end-users. While untrusted, such signals can still be
        used as hints by the authorization server to present a better user
        experience, like informing the user they need a lock screen.
      </t>
      <t>
        Error encountered during authorization can be displayed to the user in
        the browser making this a more user friendly way to instruct the user on
        how to move their device into conformance. The token endpoint (on which
        errors are less user-friendly as there's no user agent), can then
        enforce the restrictions per <xref target="token_endpoint"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        The following parameters are added to the OAuth 2.0 Authorization
        Request:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="device_posture_hint"><vspace/>
          JSON String.  URL-encoded JSON dictionary, contains the Device
        Posture Signals defined in <xref target="device_posture_signals"/>.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

        <section title="Token Endpoint Device Posture Enforcement" anchor="token_endpoint">
      <t>
        Clients that follow this specification MUST send the device posture
        signals on every request to the token endpoint.
      </t>

      <t>
      Token Endpoints SHOULD verify that the posture conforms to their
      requirements and act accordingly.
      </t>

      <t>
        The following parameters are added to all requests to the Token
        Endpoint:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="device_posture"><vspace/>
          JSON String.  URL-encoded JSON dictionary, contains the Device
        Posture Signals defined in <xref target="device_posture_signals"/>.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
      The app MUST obtain fresh device posture  information before
      every request to the Token Endpoint, and MUST NOT include stale
      information (rather, it should drop any signals it cannot freshly obtain).
      </t>

      <t>
      For token refresh requests, where the device posture has been previously
      communicated, if an attribute is missing, the Token Endpoint may choose
      to use the previous value, based on it's own policy and freshness
      requirements.
      </t>

      <t>
        If the policy does not meet requirements, the Token Endpoint
        SHOULD return the following error code:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="device_posture_invalid"><vspace/>
          Error indicating that the device posture does not meet requirements.
          The error description SHOULD contain details on why this is is the case.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security-considerations">
      <section title="Device Posture Scope" anchor="scope">
        <t>
          This specification is designed to help authorization servers enforce
          security policy (like requiring a lock screen) on end-users.
          The intent is to enforce restrictions on honest users, to force them
          to follow security practices set out by the authorization server.
          By itself, it offers no protection against malicious users,
          dishonest apps, or compromised devices.
        </t>
        <t>
          Combined with other technologies like device-based attestations and
          token binding may enable such protection, and this specification could
          be used to transmit secure signals, but that topic is out of scope
          for this specification.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Spoofed Devices" anchor="spoofed-devices">
        <t>
          It is possible to at a device level completely spoof the device
          posture. Even statements signed by the operating system are vulnerable
          to spoofing, as it's possible a statement from the real device can
          be replayed on a spoofed device, unless such statements include
          a binding to the device itself. Per <xref target="scope"/>, this topic
          is out of scope for this specification.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="App Trustworthiness" anchor="app-trust">
        <t>
          This specification is designed to allow trusted apps to report device
          posture to the authorization server to help the server enforce
          security policy on end-users. It does not by itself force apps to be
          honest, or genuine. Genuine apps (i.e. apps not lying about their
          client ID) might be dishonest about the device posture, and
          apps that are normally honest, could be spoofed, unless anti-spoofing
          countermeasures that are out of scope of this specification are employed.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <section anchor="OAuthParametersReg" title="OAuth Parameters Registration">
        <t>
          This specification registers the following value
          in the IANA "OAuth Parameters" registry
          <xref target="IANA.OAuth.Parameters"/>
          established by <xref target="RFC6749"/>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="ParametersContents" title="Registry Contents">
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>Parameter name: device_posture_hint</t>
              <t>Parameter usage location: authorization request</t>
              <t>Change controller: IESG</t>
              <t>Specification document(s): <xref target="authorization_request"/> of [[ this specification ]]</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>Parameter name: device_posture</t>
              <t>Parameter usage location: token request</t>
              <t>Change controller: IESG</t>
              <t>Specification document(s): <xref target="token_endpoint"/> of [[ this specification ]]</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="OAuthErrReg" title="OAuth Extensions Error Registration">
        <t>
          This specification registers the following error in
          the IANA "OAuth Extensions Error Registry"
          <xref target="IANA.OAuth.Parameters"/>
          established by <xref target="RFC6749"/>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="ErrorssContents" title="Registry Contents">
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>Error name: device_posture_invalid</t>
              <t>Error usage location: authorization response, token error response</t>
              <t>Related protocol extension: resource parameter</t>
              <t>Change controller: IESG</t>
              <t>Specification document(s): <xref target="token_endpoint"/> of [[ this specification ]]</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

     <section title="Device Posture Keys Registry" anchor="postureRegistry">
      <t>
        This specification establishes the
        IANA "Device Posture Keys" registry
        for Device Posture Dictionary keys.
        The registry records the Device Posture key
        and a reference to the specification that defines it.
        This specification registers the Device Posture keys
        defined in <xref target="device_posture_signals"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Keys are registered on an Expert Review
        <xref target="RFC5226"/> basis after a three-week review period on the oauth-reg-review@ietf.org mailing
        list, on the advice of one or more Designated Experts.
      </t>
        <t>
          Registration requests sent to the mailing list for review should use
          an appropriate subject
          (e.g., "Request to register Device Posture Key: screen_lock").
        </t>
        <t>
          Within the review period, the Designated Experts will either approve or
          deny the registration request, communicating this decision to the review list and IANA.
          Denials should include an explanation and, if applicable, suggestions as to how to make
          the request successful.
          Registration requests that are undetermined for
          a period longer than 21 days can be brought to the IESG's attention
          (using the iesg@ietf.org mailing list) for resolution.
        </t>
        <t>
          Criteria that should be applied by the Designated Experts includes
          determining whether the proposed registration duplicates existing functionality,
          whether it is likely to be of general applicability
          or whether it is useful only for a single application,
          whether the value is actually being used,
          and whether the registration description is clear.
        </t>
        <t>
          IANA must only accept registry updates from the Designated Experts and should direct
          all requests for registration to the review mailing list.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is suggested that the same Designated Experts evaluate these
          registration requests as those who evaluate registration requests
          for the IANA "OAuth Parameters" registry <xref target="IANA.OAuth.Parameters"/>.
        </t>

        <section title="Registration Template" anchor="postureTemplate">
          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Device Posture Signal Key:">
                <vspace/>
                The key name requested (e.g., "screen_lock").
                Names may not match other registered names in a case-insensitive manner
                unless the Designated Experts state that there is a compelling reason
                to allow an exception.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Device Posture Signal Key Description:">
                <vspace/>
                Brief description of the device posture signal
                (e.g., "Screen lock active").
              </t>
              <t hangText="Change Controller:">
                <vspace/>
                For Standards Track RFCs, state "IESG". For others, give the name of the
                responsible party. Other details (e.g., postal address, email address, home page
                URI) may also be included.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Specification Document(s):">
                <vspace/>
                Reference to the document or documents that specify the parameter,
                preferably including URIs that
                can be used to retrieve copies of the documents.
                An indication of the relevant
                sections may also be included but is not required.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Initial Registry Contents" anchor="postureRegistrations">
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">screen_lock</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description: Boolean. 'true' when the device has a screen lock enabled.
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">root_privileges</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description:  Boolean.  True if user apps can access root device privileges.
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">full_disk_encryption</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description:  Boolean. True if data stored on the
                device is fully encrypted at rest.
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">device_id</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description:  String. A unique identifier for the device.
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">device_os</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description:  String. The name of the operating system
                running on the device such as "iOS" or "Android".
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">device_os_version</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description:  String. The current version of the operating system.
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">device_vendor</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description:  String. The vendor of the device such as "Apple
                or "Google".
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">device_model</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description:  String. The model of the device
                such as "iPhone X" or "Pixel 2"
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">device_attestation</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description:  Dictionary. An attestation
                from the operating system, containing a signed-statement about
                the device and/or the app.
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">app_id</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description:  String. The platform-specific identifier (URI) for the application.
                For Android, the format of the URI is android:apk-key-hash:&lt;hash-of-apk-signing-cert&gt;.
                For iOS, the format of URI is ios:bundle-id:&lt;ios-bundle-id-of-app&gt;.
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key: <spanx style="verb">app_managed</spanx>
              </t>
              <t>
                Device Posture Signal Key Description:  Boolean. True if the app is managed by a MDM/EMM system.
              </t>
              <t>
                Change Controller: IESG
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification Document(s): <xref target="device_posture_signals"/> of [[ this specification ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>



  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6749'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5226'?>
      <reference anchor="IANA.OAuth.Parameters" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/oauth-parameters">
        <front>
          <title>OAuth Parameters</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6819'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        The following individuals contributed ideas, feedback, and wording
        that shaped and formed the final specification:
      </t>
      <t>
        Eric Sachs, John Bradley, and Andy Zmolek.
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
